Fatih SAYIN

Austin, TX 78729 | fmsayin@hotmail.com| (512) 765 3221 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

A strategic, multidisciplinary data analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Five year of previous expertise on research and data analytics combined with the best creative data visualizations, actionable insight, and perfect approximation algorithms. Proactively perfect skill sets and deep experience with the tools VBA, Python, Ipython, Pandas, SQL, MongoDB, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn, and Spark.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Queries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Tableau

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib,
- API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet.j

MOST RECENT PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Project

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

2. Project

- Name: Machine Learning Real Estate Project (The Relationship between Stock Market & Real Estate Price)
- **Description:** The purpose of this project was to build a real-estate pricing model with a dataset which we gathered from Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT). In this project 8 popular machine learning models were used, such as Decision Tree Regression, Random Forest Regression, K Nearest Neighbors Regression, Support Vector Machine, Ridge Regression, XGBoost, Lasso Regression, Baseline Model. [Team Project] **Link:** https://github.com/fmsayin/Machine-Learning-Real-Estate-Project

3. Project

- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (EuroLeague)
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DATA ANALYST

Cosmos Trading Inc., Austin, Texas, USA / January 2019 - Present

- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and pivot reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the executive board to make the correct decisions.
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy

Most Recent Project

- **Project Name:** Stock Market Analysis between 2018 2019
- **Description**: This project was about, looking at data from particularly stock market analysis. In the project, we used pandas to get stock market information, for visualization we used matplotlib, seaborn and beautiful soup and some ways of analyzing the risk of a stock.

DATA ANALYTICS & VISUALIZATION BOOT CAMP

The University of Texas at Austin, Texas, USA / October 2018 – April 2019 Completed Projects

- I. Heroes of Pymoli Game Data Analysis | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes_of_Pymoli
- II. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather_Py
- III. Rental Movie Database | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql_challange
- IV. Web-Visualization | **Link**: https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io
- V. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel
- VI. New York City Bike Analytics with Tableau | **Link**: https://github.com/fmsayin/New-York-City-Bike-Analytics-with-Tableau

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Freelance, Austin, Texas, USA / August 2016 - September 2018

- I carried on research to reach data to publish a scientific article.
- As a freelance researcher and data analyst; I did some social projects.

Completed Project

- **Project Name:** Effects of unsuccessful coup attempt happened on July 15th, 2016 in Turkey
- **Description**: After the military coup attempt, 4 million individuals were affected (500 650 individuals were arrested, 2285 educational Institutions, 1600 NGOs, 189 media outlets and 15 universities were shut down). Each institution and occupational group data were analyzed.

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Basari University Research Center, Samsun, TURKEY / September 2014 – July 2016

- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the university executive board to make the correct decisions.
- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and pivot reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Used statistical techniques for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Analyzed academic evaluations to report to the university senate and set reasonable, achievable academic goals.
- Managed student and staff, data and processes
- Wrote academic research summaries and made informed recommendations, and manage the planning and development of design and procedures for metrics reports
- Develop new reports and delegate tasks to the university president